"Hospitals Profit on Junk Food"
Put in stark terms, cardiovascular
disease claims one American life
every 39 seconds, and for most heart
attack deaths, you just keel over.
Sudden cardiac death is the first
manifestation of coronary heart disease
for the majority of individuals,
particularly among women.
So for many of these sudden
death victims, their first indication
of the presence of heart disease was
their demise. They didn't even know
they had heart disease! That's why an
ounce of prevention is worth way more
than a pound of cure, because
there is no cure for dead.
But that's why the prevention of sudden
cardiac death remains such a major
public health challenge, because most
people don't even know they're at risk.
But we've known for over a half century
when we first started autopsying
young servicemen who died in the
Korean war that coronary artery
disease begins in our youth,
even among young children.
So business as usual is simply not going
to yield the improvements necessary
to radically improve the cardiovascular
health of the United States.
But the good news is a low-risk lifestyle—
not smoking, exercising regularly,
having a prudent diet, and maintaining
a healthy weight—may be able
to wipe out the vast majority
of risk for sudden cardiac death.
So the time is now long overdue to start
aggressive preventive cardiovascular
disease programs in our schools,
our homes, our worksites.
How about starting in our hospitals?
A significant percentage of hospitals
surveyed had fast food restaurants inside
them, with Krispy Kreme topping the list.
Brilliant marketing, given that families
surveyed in hospitals with McDonald's
were twice as likely to think
McDonald's was healthy,
after all, they let it in a hospital.
But what about food served in
hospital cafeterias themselves?
Are they much better? 384 entrees
were analyzed at 14 children's hospitals
in California and only 7%
could be classified as healthy.
And just in case someone accidentally
picked the rare healthy option,
81% of eating venues in children's
hospitals made sure to have junky
impulse buys like ice cream, cookies,
and candy near the checkout register.
And 38% had signs that explicitly
encouraged unhealthy eating.
Why would they do that?
If you ask hospital cafeteria
managers that exact question,
why they don't tend to
follow nutrition standards,
why nutrition is not a top priority, it's
the same answer why unhealthy food
is sold anywhere else: the
pressure to generate profit.
Increased emphasis is being placed
on running a hospital foodservice
department as a profit center,
a bigger and bigger profit center.
It's such a metaphor for our
sickness-care system in general,
where healthy treat-the-cause
approaches are eclipsed
by the pills and procedures
that bring in the most money.
Well, what do you expect
from the private sector?
But public hospitals
don't seem much better.
A 2019 analysis of veterans' hospitals
found that all VA hospitals
contain vending machines providing a
majority of soda, candy, and junk foods
that directly conflict with our
government's own healthy food choice
recommendations such that, ironically,
hospital visits could theoretically
promote worse health. This raises
the question why any soda
or candy machines are
available our VA hospitals?
Are we trading the health
of our veterans for profits?
Maybe it's time to ban junk
food on hospital premises.
On daily rounds it is appalling to see
patients gorging on potato chips,
candy, and soda—the very foods
that may have contributed
to their admission
in the first place.
Obscene to see fast food
franchises on site, legitimizing
the acceptability and consumption
of such foods in the daily diet.
The obesity epidemic
represents a public health crisis,
but it's a public health scandal
that by legitimizing junk food,
hospitals have themselves become
a risk factor for diet-related disease.
Maybe it's time to stop
selling sickness in the hospital.
What message do residents receive
when they are fed pizza and soda pop
at grand rounds on obesity?
We need a healthcare system with
more Hippocrates and less hypocrisy.